[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net
sc radio is brought to you by the ieee
computer society by ieee software
magazine
online at computer.org software
at collide we know end users are it
admins most significant untapped
resources and key to solving the most
challenging to fix security issues
including instructing developers to set
passphrases on unencrypted ssh keys
finding plaintext two-factor backup
codes and teaching end users how to
store them securely
convincing employees to uninstall evil
browser extensions that may sell their
browser history
visit collide.com sc radio to sign up
today that's
kolide.com sc radio
enter your email when prompted to
receive your free collide gift bundle
after trial activation
you can try collide with all its
features on an unlimited number of
devices for free for 14 days no credit
card required
try it out at collide.com sc radio
hi this is phillip winston for software
engineering radio
i'm here with sergey gormanov sergey is
a co-founder of axillar and an assistant
professor at the university of waterloo
he was previously a founding team member
at algorand he received his phd from mit
where he was a microsoft phd fellow his
phd dissertation was on designing
cryptographic tools for the cloud using
lattice-based cryptography
sergei is there anything i left out of
your bio you'd like to add
no i think that pretty much sums it up
thanks phil and great to be here great
before we start here are two shows from
our archives that i found helpful in
researching this topic
episode 297 kieran james lubin on
blockchain and episode 343
john crane on ethereum and smart
contracts
so starting from the top what is
blockchain
yeah so in a very high level
what we're seeing in the blockchain
ecosystem today is that many different
networks being built right many
different blockchains so you have
networks such as bitcoin such as
ethereum you know outground cosmos polka
dot
near and the list goes on and goes on
and so blockchain interoperability at
the very core is the concept of how do
we connect all of these blockchain
systems together and allow connectivity
between applications and users at the
very end of the day today that's not
really
possible in many instances and you know
blockchain interoperability and what
we're trying to solve is precisely that
okay do we know how many blockchains are
there or how many sort of major
blockchains are there and which ones do
you expect users want to interoperate
between or is it just any interoperating
between any blockchain
yeah so i mean i think today there is
definitely
a higher
number of like dozens of blockchains
that have good usage and good use cases
right so maybe 30 to 50. there are
thousands of blockchains on their own
many of them are smaller blockchains
still today but they continue to grow
and continue to get use cases and
continue to get tractions
i do expect we're gonna see
thousands of big blockchains down the
line in the years and i think the reason
for this
is you know similar to if you look at
the history of the internet of how it
evolved right and you would see very
similar properties as we see you know in
the blockchain system today
we start with dozens of networks then it
went to hundreds then it went to
thousands many of them kind of optimized
for specific applications or specific
needs of their user base or demographics
and i think we're starting to see
a lot of the early signs and a lot of
the same momentum happened in the
blockchain systems today
okay one thing i wasn't clear about i
know cryptocurrency is only one use of
blockchains but
today i assume i can exchange
cryptocurrency from one type to another
so if i have ether and i want to use a
service that's on solana presumably i
can exchange
between those two is that
not a form of interoperability or are we
talking about something more
pervasive or more deep than that yeah i
mean i think exchanging a value through
like a centralized provider right
through an exchange is is actually a
form of interoperability right and the
centralized exchanges to date they've
been actually the only interoperable
systems that have scaled right you know
you take an asset on one chain you swap
it for an asset on the other chain
now i think we're you know in a pretty
exciting space in the blockchain system
where we're actually starting to see
interesting applications being built
right decentralized applications web3
you know open finance nfts and so on and
so forth and so for those applications
to interoperate and allow them to do
their functions and you know some of
them could be as simple as swapping an
asset from chain a to hnb or some of
them you know take a loan against my
asset but those are inherently
decentralized applications right and
like to connect them together we
similarly need decentralized and open
software stacks and a technology to do
that and so that's what you know
interoperability is about this like
allowing these applications to continue
growing to continue being you know as
scalable as some of the centralized
applications like centralized exchanges
but without having to add you know
friction and kind of concentration in
the process of centralized parties
okay yeah we're definitely going to get
more into applications in a little bit
one thing i wanted to also clarify is i
guess there's a series of documents
called erc which is kind of like
rfc is for the internet i guess these
are for ethereum and there's one called
erc20 can you explain a little bit what
this is and
how it relates maybe to the
proliferation of different types of
either blockchains or just of currencies
on blockchains
yeah no it's a great question i mean one
fundamental kind of use case of a
blockchain system is to be able to
create a new asset on top of it right so
for instance you want to
create a tokenized version of land as
property right so that's one type of
asset or you want to build your own kind
of governance token or digital coin that
represents
a business or an operation that you're
trying to set up so how can you do this
you know one way of doing it is to tell
you go and build your own chain from
scratch right then but that may be you
know it's not as simple if you're a
one-man kind of developer that wants to
have this asset being created like
overnight in a couple of hours
so platforms like ethereum and erc20
asset erc20 format are trying to solve
this by allowing people to easily create
their own serve assets or forms of
assets on top of existing blockchains
right on top of ethereum like avalanche
and you can go to other blockchains and
do this and you can do this you know in
five minutes by executing a couple of
command calls and a couple of function
calls and then you can define your own
rules for this asset how many of those
assets do you want to mint what are the
transfer ownership rights who is the
owner behind the asset and you can kind
of customize it as you need it for your
own use case and application and so the
erc20 format is you know one example of
an asset class that's easy to create
easy to use and then you as a developer
can integrate it in your application or
kind of build a use case around it
okay i think this might be related to
i've read about different layers for
blockchains different layers can you not
necessarily go through all of them but
just kind of explain from an
interoperability point of view what
layer are you interoperating at or is it
multiple layers
yeah
great question i mean i think on the
high level there's
notion of like layer ones and layer twos
right and i don't necessarily think
they're you know quite accurate in some
sense i mean layer ones i think are
pretty clear and what is a layer one for
everybody it's you know basically a
blockchain okay so you have a set of
nodes those nodes execute a consensus
protocol the consensus protocol allows
you to you know write data into this
distributed system and allows people to
read data out of it right so that's like
a layer one layer two is very similar in
that model but some of the properties of
this distributed system may be inherited
from
other systems right so for instance
security of my chain could be inherited
from a security of your chain right
through various mechanisms like transfer
rights and so on and so forth and so
that's what people refer to as layer two
but i think and for all practical
purposes it's it's a chain that's sort
of instantiated differently somehow in
the ecosystem
the way we think about interoperability
and in specifically what we're doing at
axler is we're thinking as an overlay
network that sits across multiple
blockchains right so i think one example
of overlay networks are players like
akamai right so for those that are
familiar with a traditional you know
networking and infrastructure
sir akamai sits an overlay network that
has their infrastructure built around
different isps and then it's you know
delivers service for the internet that
allows people to efficiently deliver
content from a source network to a
destination network right and so
similarly we think of axler as a similar
type of a service overlay network that
spans across multiple blockchains
and there's a network layer and on top
of it there is a sdk and an api layer
that makes it easy to interact with the
network but it sort of sits you know as
a layer above that that spans all of the
other blockchains so
i don't know what number we want to give
it
or
but you know i think that's a high level
yeah it's interesting the analogies with
the internet or with networking i guess
in some sense a blockchain is a network
you have nodes and you have connections
and like you say you have then multiple
networks and connections between
networks so it's it's interesting that
this is
new but also you know referencing stuff
that's come before you mentioned
consensus the two shows i
mentioned in the beginning have more
details we're not going to get into the
full details but
are there
many different types of consensus and
does that affect interoperability i
don't know if the proof of work and
proof of stake if those are considered
consensus or maybe those are
incentive mechanisms but just trying to
get a lay of the landscape and what
challenges it presents to you
fantastic question yeah so there are
many different types of consensus
mechanisms right there is kind of
nakamura proof of work consensus
mechanism
there is you know byzantine type of
consensus mechanisms right byzantine
consensus is a kind of traditional
consensus algorithm that has been used
at least in academic literature for many
decades but you know finally started to
find its way in the blockchain systems
as well
it has been created in various shapes
and forms you know with various
properties there are newer consensus
protocols that people have built you
know including the protocols behind our
ground like avalanche and so on and so
forth so
there are many consensus protocols and
back to your point this is exactly what
makes the interoperability as a
challenging problem right you're not
speaking with systems that have
you know the same interface or the same
properties you have to talk and
translate from systems that speak very
you know different languages have
different their formats of what is
considered for a transaction to be final
right maybe for bitcoin chain it's like
is this transaction sits deep in the
block right and that takes an hour for
other chains maybe it's just a couple of
seconds and you have instant finality
and then you have to translate the
messages from one format to another and
so on and so forth and so yeah i think
just the vast you know array of
different software stacks and consensus
protocols people have built is what
makes interoperability challenging
because you have to translate all of
these things you know in the process and
kind of back to your previous point
about centralized exchanges being
interoperable systems you actually see
you know players like coinbase take like
six months to onboard another chain that
has like very different rules
because like it's it's not a trivial
task but we have actually built kind of
a with axle there's a software stack and
a platform that makes it super easy to
onboard new chains right regardless of
with consensus mechanisms like 10 15
minutes through the platform you can run
through assuming it has you know certain
evi and evm support and we're going to
continue scaling from there so that that
was really one of the core properties
that we wanted to achieve is that we
want to keep on scaling we want to be
able to make those connections as easy
as possible without having to you know
spend six months of engineering work to
do that
sure and i guess something that comes up
a lot are the idea of a validator is
that something that's common across all
blockchains or is even that
dependent on the implementation having
validators or not i mean some ecosystems
call it differently some call them
validators some call them miners right
in bitcoin because they're using a lot
of processing power but the notion you
know is pretty similar on its own is
that
certain nodes in the system are allowed
to you know produce blocks let's say
that right and so in the bitcoin
networks those are miners in proof of
stake networks those are validators and
it is uh kind of what makes the
consensus protocol sticks right this
special nodes that are actually running
the underlying consensus mechanisms and
reaching these finality goals
okay so that gives me the sense that
each blockchain is not totally
from scratch unrelated to the other ones
there are similarities but they're
differences
which makes sense so let's talk about
programmability on blockchains was
ethereum the first programmable
blockchain or is it just the most
well-known and is
programmable blockchain is it for
implementing just smart contracts or are
there other benefits to programmability
yeah i mean i think you know actually
bitcoin was probably you know the first
programmable chain but the
programmability there was pretty limited
right so you had a notion of a script a
bitcoin script
that you can write your logic in but
it's very limited and i think ethereum i
mean i don't know all the roots behind
how they came up with the design but
they said well how can we make it more
generic so that we're not limiting the
developers to
kind of very special script and
functionalities but we can make it you
know close to
a full developer platform right it's
close to like a touring complete
language where you can write any program
and execute any function and so
indeed sort of ethereum was the first
instantiation of that vision where
developers could write their arbitrary
code in some sense right and execute
complicated logic or simple logic
on top of the platform and then the
network of validators and you know
miners in that case validates that logic
and allows them to execute it in a
distributed system
okay we're going to linger on
programmability just for a little bit
since we are software engineering so i
read i think it was the ethereum yellow
paper i'm not sure if there's a white
paper and a yellow paper but i think the
yellow paper had the
machine codes or the op codes i guess
for virtual machine and it described
them in detail i was pretty interested
to see that how would a developer write
software that runs on that virtual
machine i know say with
c sharp or java you write in a higher
level language it gets compiled down to
the virtual machine is that how it works
with ethereum or other blockchains
yeah pretty similar right you have you
know solidity i think is a common
language that's used in the
kind of ethereum based execution
environment and then developers write
their code in uh solidity and then they
take that code they surf compile it with
a specific accelerated version that
produces the byte code and then this
byte code is what gets actually deployed
on the chain itself right and so you
know you do have to be careful in the
process to make sure that you're
compiling you know using the right
version of the compiler that the chain
interprets and understands correctly so
that you don't end up you know faulty
byte code and so on and so forth but
yeah i think you know solidity i think
is actually pretty straightforward as a
language to use kind of if you're
familiar with you know javascript or
python like you get a grasp of solidity
i think pretty easily
that being said you do have to be you
know
very careful not to introduce the
security vulnerabilities right then you
can talk about it but i think that's
what makes it challenging to once you
deploy your application
unless you put some type of upgrade
logic it becomes immutable on chain
right so what that means is that the
code is so fixed in you can't just
easily push an upgrade button if you
find a vulnerability into it you can
work around it and you can put you know
an upgrade logic around it but you're
gonna have to do that explicitly but by
default the code is immutable so you
have to be extra careful to do audits
right to find vulnerabilities before the
code is deployed to carefully check all
the security conditions because once
it's out there it's run by a
decentralized system and
you can't take it down
yeah one detail i wondered about that is
how many different nodes are potentially
executing your same program is that i
assume there's a lot of redundancy there
but is that
you know dozens or hundreds of times or
you know is it cross-checked like what's
actually running your byte code
it depends on the you know blockchain in
some of them it's depending on how many
validators you have so every validator
would have to execute it so if it's you
know dozens of validators then it's
dozens if it's hundreds of validators
that it's hundreds
in some systems you have nodes that are
also executing a similar byte code right
so there is a redundancy there as well
so
yeah i think that's you know sort of
quite important in order to reach the
consensus right because you have a
system that you're trying to execute in
a decentralized environment and your
goal is to
reach a consensus on the state of that
system
even in the presence of malicious actors
right so you can't trust a single person
execute all the functions you have to
trust a decentralized sort of committee
or validators to do that that being said
there are ways to kind of simplify some
of this there are things like zero
knowledge proofs where you can you know
change the program and model a little
bit and require only a smaller subset of
validators to execute the logic but by
default it is a large number of
validators and some nodes that are that
are executed and all the logic
okay so we talked about ethereum sort of
up the ante for the degree of
programmability are blockchains that
have come out since then
sort of matching that level of
programmability or is it getting even
more customizable like what's kind of
the direction for programmability have
we already reached
sort of maximum generic capability or is
it still evolving
so programmability i think has been
two levels i think one of them is at the
core blockchain level itself right so
projects like cosmos and polkadot for
instance they ask themselves the
question well what if a developer
doesn't just want to build a smart
contract but they want to customize the
rules of the underlying blockchain right
so for instance customize the number of
validators or customize what the upgrade
protocol should look like for the
underlying network right so those
ability to program the network layer
itself
and so projects like cosmos or polkadot
they allowed you to kind of program on a
lower level than the underlying network
and this distributed database so that's
one avenue of expansion and many
projects can have benefited it build
their own software stacks customize you
know number of validators their
programming environments and so on and
so forth and then the second i think you
know programmability aspect is like what
language do the developers actually
interact with with the system right and
solidity and ethereum virtual machine
are definitely examples
there are others so there are people
writing code in rust there are people
kind of writing code in javascript so
for instance agorik right and so they
build their own chain and with their own
programming environment on top of it and
so the programmability on top of these
blockchains i think continues expanded
to support different languages and
different frameworks that being said i
think most of the change today
that have gained traction there are kind
of solidity and ethereum based outside
of ethereum because that's what early
developers were familiar with and they
know how to just take their code and
kind of deploy it on it on a different
chain and continue scaling from there
but i do expect to see i think more
variety over the coming years okay let's
talk about applications from the user's
point of view for just a little bit and
then we'll dive into existing
operability methods and then the axle or
network in particular
so
can you give some examples of
distributed applications that would be
improved with better interoperability so
something that's maybe possible today
but would be much easier or something
that's not possible today that would
become possible if interoperability were
sort of a solved problem or a easy thing
for users to do
yeah i mean i think one example is to go
back to this application of exchange
right so you know today we're starting
to see early examples of g5 applications
that allow people to swap one token for
another so at its core if you build one
of these applications let's say on an
ethereum chain
then the assets that you can allow users
to swap
are limited to these erc20 tokens that
are built on ethereum right so you can't
take an asset like bitcoin and allow
them to swap in in your application you
can take you know an asset from a cosmos
chain and allow it to be swapped for an
asset on an ethereum base chain so what
who can do this only centralized
exchanges can do this right and as we go
back to what we described but these defy
applications you know want to continue
expanding reaching more users getting
more distribution and liquidity and so
this is a simple example where you can
host this application on one of these
chains
and then connect with interoperability
layers to allow users to swap an
arbitrary asset in the ecosystem through
your application that may be hosted on a
specific particular chain
and so i think that's you know one
example you can we can continue thinking
about them like another one is for
instance nft transfers right
so nft has been issued a lot over the
last year
but many people want to see applications
around them for instance i want to take
a loan against my piece of art
if my art and nft representation of it
was minted on one chain but the
application where i want to take a loan
against it lives on a different chain
like i can't do this right okay i can't
even go to a centralized exchange
because what do i do i sell my art so i
can take some other asset you know i
want to keep my art and i want to take
an asset from a different chain so kind
of centralized exchanges don't work at
all in this case and so through
connecting the chains directly through a
decentralized protocol you can allow
users to
still keep their art take a loan against
this lock it in some application on a
different chain take an asset and return
and use it somewhere else and kind of
continue from there
that's interesting i didn't quite
understand that even simply exchanging
could have benefits of being
decentralized
so i guess the idea is a centralized
exchange could be
a single commercial entity that could
decide to change the rules or to take it
down or maybe
an attacker or something takes it down
or it gets hacked are those kind of some
of the concerns that people have with
centralized exchanges
i mean i think those are some of the
concerns but at the very core of it i
think kind of a decentralized open stack
allows people to continue you know
innovating and reaching audiences that
centralized stacks cannot do on the very
core right so you know if there is a new
algorithm that you want to experiment
with if there is a new type of a way of
an exchange that you want to experiment
with you can
take a look at other people's code you
can take a look at you know others
people data you can understand what
they've done you can understand how
they've kind of captured users you can
replicate it in a similar environment
than a similar decentralized stack and
get a distribution from all of these
blockchains from day one right like
centralized exchanges don't have those
things they they're bound by
you know an entity a jurisdiction right
and an operator behind them that's
responsible for the distribution
and i think just the power of building
around open systems actually allows you
to go much faster and innervate much
faster where i can keep on building on
your work you can keep on building on my
work we can keep on improving things we
can reach all of the users same user
base right all the systems are open so
it becomes a question of who has a
better product as opposed to you know
who has spent more on marketing right
than like satisfying regulatory regimes
and you know figuring out like how to
create another partnership with another
like provider
yeah i can see that how about one more
application that's i wouldn't say not
financial but maybe less you know purely
financial is there any other that come
to mind that are maybe not possible
today but you could see
happening i'm just trying to frame the
benefits of interoperability for people
that maybe are not clear exactly
yeah so i mean i think one example with
blockchain such as filecoin so i know
for those of you that are not familiar
falcon and ipfs are decentralized
blockchains and systems that were built
to
store information and knowledge in a
lawn
forever effectively right so you can
think of it as an immutable ledger where
you can write
lots of data
and people kind of host their websites
on it people kind of host their you know
nfts music arts and so on and so forth
right so it's a it's the ledger that has
been optimized to store you know i think
as they call like a human's most
important information right so it's an
archive of information on its own that
ledger right now
you know in some sense kind of lives in
an isolated system right and there are
apis to interact with it and there are
ways to connect with it but you can't
really build you know interesting
applications around that data as of you
know right now and so by connecting this
chain that has been designed around the
specific use case in mind with other
chains that have you know
programmability for instance right we
can continue expanding you know
interesting applications around it right
so maybe
you can host
a social distribution application on one
chain you can connect it with something
like ipfs or file code on another chain
you can read data from it you can write
data back to it and so then you get to
interact with this two different
environments that have been optimized
for different use cases one is for file
storage another one for programmability
and you can compose them together
time scale db from your friends at time
scale is the leading open source
relational database with support for
time series data time series data is
time stamped so you can measure how a
system is changing time series data is
relentless and requires a database like
time scale db with speed and petabyte
scale
time scale db is the postgres you know
and love with time series superpowers
familiarity flexibility speed that's
time scale
visit them today at tsdb.co
se radio
that's tsdb.co
that's really interesting so i can
imagine instead of evolving you know one
blockchain to rule them all that has
every capability we could tie them
together and mix and match you mentioned
ipfs i think that's the interplanetary
file system is that what it stands for
yeah that's an ambitious project but i
think it makes sense so i guess that
leads to like a question which is you
know how big are these blockchains in
terms of data so like the blockchain is
a chain of immutable blocks and you know
the validators in some cases have to
download the whole history is that
becoming an obstacle is that sort of
just happened to be a size that
validators can download or where is that
all heading
yeah
most of the blockchains you have
multiple modes of operation right you
can run sort of an archival node that
stores all of the data that has ever
been produced by this chain you can run
uh serve a full node and you can think
of it a full node as a node that stores
enough data to be able to validate
transactions on the latest state of the
system but nothing old right so if there
is a transaction that happened in the
past that's no longer relevant i don't
necessarily need to store it because you
know it cannot be double spend it cannot
be executed again and i'm not in the
business of storing you know old and
archival data right so in that case it's
a full node it's typically like you know
a fraction of the archival nodes in
terms of size so maybe we're talking
about you know depending on the chain
from tens of gigabytes to maybe hundreds
of gigabytes of data but it's only sort
of the active state of the database you
also have
modes of operations such as light
clients right so unlike clients or even
lighter objects maybe they only store
you know a couple gigabytes or even less
and they only store information relevant
to them so if i want to monitor a
specific account and i want to
understand what transactions are
happening from this account
i can do that or i can talk to another
full node and ask them for some
information or i can talk to archival
node and ask them for a state of uh you
know an archival transaction
so you have this different modes of
operation right and the store
requirements of course differ if you
want to be an archival note that's the
heaviest if you want to have a light
note that's the lightest
that being said i want to mention that
there are techniques to reduce storage
as well right in all of the blockchain
systems so i think proof systems or like
zero knowledge proof systems and
protocols like mina i think are some
examples that apply
more advanced kind of cryptographic
protocols in order to compactify the
state and compactify the information
so that it can be validated more
efficiently and those you know don't
have to store hundreds of gigabytes they
can store only a couple actually
megabytes of data or even kilobytes of
data in order to validate state
transition so all of the things are
possible you know it's just a question
of
how and when we get there
yeah i mean that really rings true with
sort of how active the space is how much
experimentation is going on how quickly
things are evolving so whenever you see
a problem that looks like it's going to
be a limitation or sort of a hard stop
and it's going to halt progress it seems
like there's people that are working
around it or discovering new techniques
so that's an interesting aspect of the
space so getting into interoperability a
little more specifically let's first
talk about some existing methods again
like with the layers i don't think we
need to go into them all but i'm just
going to list off some and maybe you can
pick ones that
particularly
are good at contrasting with axler's
approach or that axler did build on or
just trying to like frame what are the
possibilities here so we talked about
centralized exchanges already as a form
of interoperability there's something
i've read about side chains wrapped
assets token bridges
federated oracles just just kind of
paint the picture of i guess what led up
to axelr and what methods are or what
methods are being developed in parallel
or just give us some idea yeah so i
think effectively what happened in the
ecosystem is the following we had you
know early examples of blockchain
bitcoin ethereum right like 2013 2015
interesting applications
then 2017 to 2020 all of these other
chains have been built right many of
them optimized for different consensus
protocols and so on and so forth
what has happened in parallel in there
is that people realize that
interoperability is going to be an
important topic right and so some early
examples of interoperability are
projects like cosmos or polka dot that
talk about interoperability within their
own ecosystems right so i call it sort
of consensus dependent interoperability
so meaning that they have designed
protocols that have their notion of
side chains or chains that can talk to
each other through the protocol that's
kind of native to the underlying
consensus
so that works fine but those protocols
do not scale and don't work to connect
with other ecosystems right so if
another chain doesn't have the same
protocol baked in at the consensus layer
it's very hard to connect and interact
with it and so then the last year we saw
an array of all of those
solutions that you mentioned like from
you know token bridges like federated
oracles and so on and so forth
and the issue with all of them is
they're actually centralized parties
that are solving the interoperability
right so just like centralized exchange
can allow you to swap one asset to
another you can build a centralized
database that allows people to take
their token you know wrap it in some
other form and move it on another chain
its representation
but in this process because there is a
centralized party that you rely on we're
adding a a lot of friction in this
process b a lot of trust assumptions so
if this centralized party that move the
asset kind of goes down or gets shut
down or has a quality of service issues
then
the representation of the asset that you
obtain on a different chain can no
longer be moved anywhere else right like
you're kind of stuck with it so you're
pretty much losing it and finally they
don't allow for composability of
applications right like as we talked
about earlier if you have an application
on chain a and you have an application
on chain b
how do you allow them to talk to one
another right well if you talk into a
centralized party on the back end well
might as well just build a centralized
database and a centralized application
like doesn't make sense and so this is
where kind of the world that we were
stuck in over the last year and now that
kind of the way we approached axler and
the way we've designed the stack is to
satisfy a couple core properties
one keep it decentralized from day one
so it's an open consensus it's an open
system where anybody can join and run a
validator you can run a node you know if
our validators go down there's a state
you can take it you can run your own
validator right and kind of continue
working with the data itself
two
make it easier to create connections
with different ecosystems so just like
we have you know consensus-specific
protocols and centralized parties can
actually integrate with them we want to
have a similar property where a
decentralized system can understand
multiple consensus protocols and
interact with them
so that was the second property
and the third one is a kind of a general
programmability and composability that
we're talking about right allowing
different message requests to pass
through the network
and allowing developers to customize
what those messages that they want to
pass right so we talked about you know
three use cases today but if you have
you know four fifth tenth a hundredth
use case we still want to be able to
support it and you know you shouldn't
have to go and ask us well could you
deploy this protocol could you do this
for me like no it's an open system it's
an open programming environment where
people come in and code and kind of
continue passing the data as they want
through the system and not have to rely
on a kind of centralized operator behind
the scenes
okay let's get into some specifics about
your solution so
we talked about analogies with internet
i think one of your pieces of technology
is this cross chain gateway protocol
which you draw an analogy with bgp which
is the border gateway protocol used by
internet routers can you explain the
analogy a little more and also just dig
into what this cross chain gateway
protocol is like
yeah so i mean i think on a high level
for those that are you know familiar
with protocols like bgp like those
protocols at the very core
are responsible for connecting multiple
autonomous networks right and being able
to route information and deliver
information from them in one shape on
form and so they're actually fundamental
and i think a good example you could
actually see from a couple
months ago when facebook misconfigured
their bgp routes and what end up
happening like the whole facebook
network and like applications like
what's up were just disconnected from
the rest of the world right and so
that's exactly you know a use case for
bgp protocol where its network however
it was configured was talking with the
rest of the world and other networks and
bgp was a protocol that make those kind
of translations and connections in the
process and so axle as a network you can
think of it as a similar type of you
know route and layer right that
underneath it has certain
functionalities that allow you to
configure these routes across different
chains so you can come in and you can
say okay i want to make a connection to
this ecosystem a i want to make a
connection to this ecosystem b here's
the path that's going to you know happen
from a chain a to a chain b and along
that path the assets or the information
can flow
right so and then
our question gateway protocol is simply
you know a set of commands and a set of
api is in a set of kind of standard
transactions that we expose that will
allow to configure all of these
different rules and make these new
connections across different ecosystems
and our overlay network underneath it
will support these functionalities
that's interesting so are you saying
that there actually could be
interoperability paths that go through
multiple chains and sort of how many
chains might be possible or is it a
question of finding a sort of a
point-to-point
connection
yeah so i think
it's an interesting question and i think
the answer is that i don't know how it's
going to shape up and i think we'll see
right if you look at the
you know history of
kind of the internet again then you have
you know hundreds of thousands of
networks right that's mostly
you have to go through like six or seven
hops to go from a source to a
destination right those are like the
averages in the blockchain systems that
becomes a little bit trickier because
even though you can technically go
through multiple hubs every hop that you
take along the way you're going to have
to take some trust assumptions in the
process right because if i go through
your network and i rely for your network
to verify information and relate to some
other network
then i'm trusting your network i'm
trusting my network i'm trusting the
destination network and so on and so
forth right so the more hops that you
add in some sense you know the more
trust assumptions that you have to make
so
that's why i think one of the things
that we're starting to see is you know
axler or like cosmos hubs they're
effectively serving as this you know
universal routing networks right that
have a trust you know underneath it but
then they connect with many other
ecosystems and then you know you only
need to trust that a single network to
go from a to b as opposed to having to
trust you know three or four different
networks if there are pairwise
connections in this process how it's
going to continue shaping out i mean i
think we'll see it's an interesting
question because the properties this is
where the properties of the blockchain
networks and the internets are diverging
a little bit right on the internet the
network on itself is unreliable right
and the there are no security properties
from packet delivery for the most part
you tell me the packet i have to build
another application layer protocol on
top of it to verify that packet but in
blockchain we at the very core want to
have this verifiability and authenticity
property and so that's why having these
kind of hubs in the middle between all
of these different ecosystems makes a
lot more sense
okay and a second protocol i think this
was mentioned in your white paper i
think that might be where i'm getting
this was this cross chain
transfer protocol so if the gateway
protocol is going to find a path between
two blockchains or a path yeah i guess
between two blockchains this cross-chain
transfer protocol is going to actually
transfer the token or the contract or
the asset or what's it going to transfer
yeah so the gateway protocol is a kind
of a network layer protocol that you
know responsible for
executing the message and delivering
from one source to the destination and
executing along the path and the
transfer protocol is more you can think
of it as an application layer protocol
that allows developers to
you know write a message on the source
chain in a specific format to
an underlying gateway and then the cross
chain sort of gateway protocol will take
that message you know route it deliver
it to the destination chain understand
how it has been executed and call the
receiving application on the destination
chain right so the transfer protocol is
you can think of it as a layer above the
network layer that makes it easier for
the applications to interact and benefit
from all of this cross-chain
infrastructure okay one term i saw i'm
not sure if it's totally related to this
was a threshold account is that
something to do with this transfer
yeah so whenever you execute in kind of
cross-chain functionality you have to do
two types of requests you have to
process like read requests and write
requests right so i need to be able to
read from a source chain a and i need to
be able to write on a source chain b
right so read requests you know they're
somewhat straightforward to do like you
can call a node of the chain and then
you have to have a kind of consensus or
a majority of people that are calling
all those different nodes and finalizing
transactions for the right request you
have to
allow
you know a set of validators or a set of
parties in order to collectively
authorize write operations on the
destination chain right and you can
execute those things in multiple ways
you know threshold cryptography multi
signatures various like proof systems
they're all examples that can enable you
with the right functionality that
effectively says that if you have let's
say a hundred validators you know a
majority of them or some subset of them
need to collectively authorize a message
or sign a message in order for that
message to be valid on another account
or another destination chain right so
threshold cryptography multiparty
cryptography multi-signatures they're
all
examples of protocols that can allow
people to collectively authorize a
decision
okay and you mentioned that low-level
internet protocols don't typically have
anything to do with security or any
promises of
security but obviously with blockchain
dealing with financial assets it's a big
concern so i saw it broken out into
these terms trust high safety high
liveness i guess decentralized stress
high safety high liveness are those
three different things that are worth
teasing apart or is it it's just all
security
there are i think worth teasing apart
right because i think security is so
generic that
in some sense it doesn't mean anything
right until you know what it means so
yeah i think those three kind of
decentralized security is i think
something we talked about already which
is a property of you know not having to
trust a single operator and having a
protocol and a cut a system that can be
supported by anybody right in the
community so that's a decentralized
property
safety and liveness those are core
properties of
consensus mechanisms right so liveness
says
under what conditions is my system going
to continue making progress right how
many nodes do you have to participate in
the protocol
how many you know if the protocol like
aborts how do we resume it and so on and
so forth and then safety is in a core
property of any blockchain system that
that's what allows us to trust it right
so meaning that
it allows us to verify that a block of
transaction or a specific transaction
is valid according to the rules of the
consensus protocol
right even in the presence of malicious
actors and this is what traditional
distributed systems don't have right if
there's a single like malicious actor in
a traditional decentralized system they
can typically you know corrupt data of
many other parties and nobody will
notice it but in a blockchain system
that's what kind of a prevents some of
these properties
is that some malicious validators cannot
cause harm in the system and like affect
other people to take a different ground
truth as the verifiable information that
just could not happen
okay
so is axler a delegated proof-of-stake
mechanism is that the consensus
mechanism or is that the incentive
mechanism
it's more so of an incentive mechanism
right so how do you run a consensus
across validators and that's what's
called you know delegated proof of stake
consensus similar to projects like
cosmos or polka dot where
users that have a certain token that
have voting power in the system they can
delegate this voting power to operators
that are running you know full nodes and
participating in the consensus and those
validators then kind of serve in the
consensus on behalf of the users with
their voting power right so delegation
is this process of users simply
delegating their voting power to another
validator that guarantees a certain
uptime for everybody else in the system
okay so how many delegates are there
does this fluctuate over time and how
are they selected just trying to give an
idea of sort of the dynamic runtime
aspect here like what's kind of really
going on
yeah i mean how are they selected
they're selected based on the voting
power that users delegate to them right
so everybody chooses who they want to
delegate their stake to and then you can
say well let me take you know the first
50 validators and those are the
validators that are going to run
consensus or you can take you know first
hundred or first 200 and you know it is
a parameter in the system but it's a
parameter that gets adjusted and will be
adjusted depending on you know
scalability and kind of other
constraints that we're seeing on the
network i think for us we're going to
start with something like 50 validators
but it's a kind of tunable parameter in
the system that you can keep on
increasing as you need to so would it be
correct to say that axelr is a
blockchain or it has a blockchain or it
uses a blockchain what's kind of the the
relationship there
yeah i mean excellent network uses
consensus and blockchain in order to
process cross-chain transactions right
so
okay that makes sense and
i guess i came across another term here
was read write oracle is that fair
characterization of how axillar works or
is that something else
yeah no i think that's a fair
characterization right kind of for an
application to talk with other
ecosystems
you need to support you know read
requests and write requests right so in
this case you can think of axler as you
know this protocol in a network that you
can ask to pull the information or write
information on your behalf and the
network processes under the hood
okay you mentioned cosmos and polka dot
a few times are these things
axler would have to interoperate with or
are you trying to
replace them in some form or what's the
relationship between these different
projects
yeah we're interoperating across them
right so actually accelerate stack was
built around kind of cosmos sdk which
kind of going back to
your question earlier about the
programmabilities what allowed us to
program the network layer itself right
so we have to customize the validators
customize the logic that they're
executing and so we build around the
cosmos sdk
and through our protocols we can connect
with both polkadot ecosystems as well as
other ecosystems we also supporting kind
of cosmos native interoperability
protocols like ibc and doing kind of
translation in the middle between that
protocol and our protocol to talk with
polka dot so yeah through excel those
ecosystems effect will now become
interconnected
okay how about axel or the project and
the company is it a standard
venture-backed company or will any part
of the governance itself be distributed
through a distributed autonomous
organization or some other mechanism
just trying to understand the
relationship between the company and the
project i guess
yeah i mean there is a you know kind of
an acceler company that's building an
initial implementation of the software
and the protocol right that being said
the network itself and the governance
around it is going to be decentralized
and open down the line
it has a similar upgrade protocol like
other proof of stake networks have like
built around cosmos decay where a
community can propose a change if that
change is implemented by either our
software development team or some other
development teams that change can be
adopted in the consensus or in the rules
new integrations can be made and so on
and so forth and yeah users can you know
participate in the governance propose
upgrades propose changes to the
parameters like numbers of validators
rewards and so on and so forth you know
i think we're definitely going to be
continuing to to contribute but it is an
open system and that's what makes it
really scale is the fact that anybody
can contribute and anybody can build
around it
okay we're kind of starting to wrap up
but what are some milestones coming up
for axle or either the protocol or the
company in 2022 like what do you see as
some of your goals
yeah we're continuing to scale actively
and starting to actually deploy our
network on the mainnet right so i think
a couple of weeks ago we announced that
we started the rollout of the network so
that means we're starting you know we
built initial connections across half a
dozen of ecosystems first use cases and
asset transfer applications and similar
ones are starting to go live and we're
going to continue
turning on the network over the next you
know four six months gradually turn
around various functionalities that
we've been working on on boarding
ecosystem tools like validators
developers dashboards and
really the next years for us will be how
do we take every application and
allow it to go cross chain and allow it
to go multi-chain right and so we're
going to work closely with our developer
community with different applications
and different platforms to give them
this capability over the next year and
alongside with it you know we'll be
building on the back end and kind of
supporting all the infrastructure okay
we'll talk about how people can find out
more in a second but taking a step back
what developments are you monitoring for
blockchain in general this year that
would impact xlr and interoperability
sort of what's happening in the space
that you're tracking
we're always tracking of you know new
interest in ecosystems new interesting
applications and new interesting use
cases right so some chains
have been recently launched some chains
are going to launch over the coming
months or weeks different applications
have been built around those and so
we're keeping a close eye and you know
figuring out where we can help those
applications or those chains go global
in some sense and that's what a primary
driver of how we think about our
development than our roadmap is
okay a lot of companies and startups
they say that the founders started them
to solve a particular problem that was
personal to them
if interoperability continues to become
more robust and and more
fluid and easier for users what
personally are you most looking forward
to as an application that you'd like to
see available
i mean i think to me an ability to just
frictionlessly transact and go
across multiple ecosystems is what i
would like to see right i think
you know as a personal example i think i
onboarded a friend to a blockchain
ecosystem and i told him like you know
go use this wallet go use this
application and he started playing with
it like he started generating like
hundreds of transactions on on one chain
it was a great and like oh i became you
know a liquidity provider i've never
heard that term before right like now
i'm a liquidity provider like where can
i provide liquidity for my ten dollars
right like in traditional finance that's
impossible right you know you take your
ten dollars and you can you can't do
anything with it and so just seeing like
you know regular audience and folks that
are not familiar with the blockchain
unlocking these different kind of a use
cases and the power of decentralized
finance and other open systems i think
it's super powerful at the same time
this trend saw another application on
ethereum and he started to use some
bridges and then and then we lost him
right and then he realized that once he
gets to ethereum he has to pay you know
300 bucks in transaction fee like his
transfer was stuck and he couldn't get
out
so that's how we lost them and i don't
want to see that i think i want to i
want to continue on boarding you know
regular users that can understand the
power of these applications give them
new opportunities that they could not
have behind traditional closed systems
and you know see them build their own
use cases around those
yeah yeah i've heard about the fees can
get pretty significant in some cases
so
one question is
if axler was created to work with some
blockchains that perhaps were designed
long before axler existed
going forward how
do you see new blockchains
how would they be developed to work with
interoperability from day one like what
kind of changes
now that interoperability is a thing for
future blockchains
yeah so we have done two things i think
one
we have like an arbitrary support for
common software stacks so meaning that
if your chain supports
like ethereum virtual machine or
solidity you actually don't need to do
anything to integrate with axler okay so
it's like 10 commands will run through
the network or you can run
and then you can integrate your chain
you can optimize your consensus kind of
governance rules and in that case were
agnostic right so we integrated the
software programming interface if that's
not available for you then at the
network layer we have really built these
kind of core primitives that you need to
make other connections simpler that you
can leverage right and that comes down
to those read functionalities those
right functionalities and those
cross-chain process and translation
functionalities and so the network layer
we have build those where
if you have a very custom environment
and so on and so forth you want to
integrate with you can reuse those
building blocks and write your own
translation layer to integrate your
blockchain with all other ecosystems and
what we have done is like exposing those
building blocks and functionalities that
are needed for interoperability at the
very core
yeah that's where you can really see how
things evolve where you're you're
building on everything that came before
but if you're adding significant new
capability then the next person is
building upon that
collide sends employees important timely
and relevant security recommendations
for their linux mac and windows devices
right inside slack
collide is perfect for organizations
that want to move beyond a traditional
lockdown model to one where employees
are educated about security and device
management while they're fixing
important problems
visit collide.com se radio to sign up
today
that's
kolide.com se radio
enter your email when prompted to
receive your free collide gift bundle
after trial activation
you can try collide with all its
features on an unlimited number of
devices for free for 14 days no credit
card required
try it out at collide.com
se radio
how can listeners learn more about axler
and blockchain interoperability in
general whether it's a website or a
podcast and i can put this in the show
notes so people can see it
yeah i think you know to get started to
learn about xlr you can visit our
website actually dot network you can
follow us on twitter axl core handle i
encourage everybody to sign up with
discord it's a very vibrant developer
community we have over you know 30 000
developers that are signed up on it we
have there's testnet channels we have
there's like social community programs
where we engage folks to you know
develop content or write their own
tutorials around the network or how to
use this functionalities
and if you have any questions there
again feel free to ask lots of people
that are watching those channels and
we'll help you answer them and yeah i
think just get engaged start building i
think that's the best way to learn
okay can i ask of the name axelr is that
where does that come from
yeah great question well a big
constraint by picking a name is making
sure the domain is available
so that
that was a big factor but you know i
think as my co-founder and i we were
thinking through it you know where
actually there is a play on words on
accelerating the ecosystem right so
that's a play on words on that
okay and how about you personally do you
have any social media or blog or
anything that people could follow
yeah i mean i think easiest place to
start is to follow me on twitter it's
sergey underscore nog
from there you can find a couple links
to my website like some white papers
that we wrote over the years kind of
standards and things like that
okay i'll put those in the show notes
also thanks for your time sergey this is
phillip winston for software engineering
radio thanks for listening thanks
phillip it was great being here
thanks for listening to sc radio an
educational program brought to you by
ieee software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at
se-radio.net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on linkedin facebook twitter or through
our slack channel at scradio.slack.com
[Music]
you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of sc radio
is licensed under creative commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening
[Music]